[WATSON gasps]
This elaborate plan.
Tell me, what was
their end goal?
You're a man who
seeks out mysteries.
There's no satisfaction
without a solution.
And you want to know who created
the ultimate mystery, don't you?
So shoot me and
you'll have your answer!
[gun fires]
[gasps]
[grunts]
[WATSON] Soon after solving
the murder of Lord Drebber.
Sherlock's face was splashed
all over the newspapers.
Almost overnight,
he came to prominence.
Ever since,
we've had many visitors
at two, two, one,
B Baker Street.
Without fail, Sherlock solved
each case brought our way.
One after another.
And yet, while his fame as
a detective continues to rise,
within him, I sense
a storm brewing...
...more and more.
[HOLMES grunts]
Such tedium.
What?
I'm at a loss how things
ended up this way.
With a mind like yours,
you ought to be overjoyed at the
prospect of drowning in riddles.
I've no idea what's
to complain about--
Bah!
I seek impenetrable mysteries,
John, not these banal chores!
Oh? Like what?
What else? The biggest
mystery I've yet to solve.
[HOLMES] Who wanted my name
written in Drebber's blood
daring me to crack the case?
Hope called them his benefactor.
The mastermind who
orchestrated the crime.
I swear, I'll reveal who they
are and what their objective is.
And, until then?
[HOLMES grunts]
I wish to be alone for a while.
Very well.
[BARBER 10A] I've heard several
stories about your exploits,
Inspector Lestrade.
[LESTRADE coughs]
Careful, sir!
I don't want Scotland Yard
coming after me!
[HOLMES]
During the case on the Noahtic,
Enders was set up
by a mastermind.
Later, Lord Drebber
is murdered by Hope
under the direction of
some unknown individual.
[HOLMES grunts]
[HOPE] Sherlock Holmes.
I've heard much about you.
[HOPE] I have a deal
which might intertest you.
Pull the trigger.
End my life and I'll
give you what you want.
Answer to the ultimate mystery.
The identity of the person
who was directing me.
The one who plotted Drebber's
murder, start to finish.
They hold you in high regard.
And to such a degree,
they wanted your name
left at the crime scene.
This was a challenge to see
if you could solve the case,
and thus prove you were
a worthy opponent.
How can I describe 'em?
You'll never meet another
with such an incredible mind.
The moment I stepped foot
at Drebber's mansion
at the appointed time,
the door swung open
as if by some magic,
and there was nary
a soul around to interfere.
My benefactor truly
is a criminal genius!
[HOLMES] And someone
like that wishes to test me?
But why? To what end?!
[grunts]
[HOLMES]
What if, at this very moment...
[HOLMES groans]
[laughing]
[HOLMES]
Meanwhile,
they're still out there
somewhere, free to kill.
[laughing]
- -[gun fires]
- -[gasps]
[gun firing]
[HUDSON panting]
John! What's going on?
I'm not entirely sure!
But I definitely know
where it came from!
Sherlock! What--?
[BOTH gasp]
It appears we've
discovered the triggerman.
[LESTRADE] I heard shots!
Are you all right?
Well, we are, but Sherlock...
I see. So the shots
were from you?
[HOLMES]
Yeah, to get you to come up.
[grunts]
[HOLMES] You're far too
predictable.
At this hour, you're off-duty
getting a routine trim
at the nearby barber.
[gasps] Then come get me
like a normal person!
[HOLMES]
Lestrade.
Have there been any
recent cases involving
the sudden deaths
of aristocrats?
That's rather specific.
Why are you inquiring?
[HOLMES] Just tell me.
Have there been any?
[LESTRADE]
Hmm.
[HOLMES] Now that I no longer
have a line on this fellow,
I have no choice but to
grasp at any possibility
no matter how slim.
[LESTRADE] Well actually, I
heard the Viscount of Redshire
passed away on
his estate in York.
Tell me more!
[GROUP gasps]
[LESTRADE]
Let's see. As I recall,
he wrote a note saying he was
going for late night walk,
then collapsed near
the lakefront.
The man was ill and there
was no sign of foul play,
so the death was ruled natural.
Now that I've told you,
what are your intentions?
We're taking a trip to York.
And why would we do that?
Isn't it obvious?
To see whether or not
his death was a homicide.
But I just said--!
[LESTRADE]
For heaven's sake.
I was more than willing
to humour you and
re-examine Lord
Redshire's death,
but only because I thought
you'd uncovered some new facts.
We're here.
After the viscount left his
mansion for an evening walk,
where exactly did the
body ultimately end up?
Should be... Yeah.
That's right.
It was right beside
the base of that oak tree.
Several days have passed.
If this was a crime,
I rather suspect there aren't
any clues left to be found.
[HOLMES] Mind your own
business and keep quiet!
[RAILWAYMAN 10A]
Passengers for London!
Your train will be departing
from platform three!
If you haven't boarded at this
time, please do so immediately!
Damn it. I came all
the way to York for nothing.
The old man croaked
from illness.
What a waste of time.
[laughs] What'd I say?
Looks like you bet
on the wrong horse.
[LESTRADE gasps]
Ahem! Think I'll go buy
a paper for the ride home.
I'll find you later
and catch a drink.
Well then, see you aboard,
Inspector Lestrade!
God. Why couldn't
you die properly?
To hell with death by illness.
Holmes! Really!
You're acting like a child.
Just because things didn't
end up going your way--
This is unbecoming of you.
Damnnit, I'm outta lights.
John, gimme a match.
No, I think not!
And you know that this excess
is bad for your health!
You should quit!
Would you shut up
and just give me
a blasted match already?
Why must the most brilliant man
I've ever met lack such decency?
Ugh. This useless doctor
can't even light a cigarette!
What is that supposed to mean?
This entire mystery
would've been solved by now
if you hadn't gone
and interfered!
I beg your pardon?
You heard! Why'd you
have to stop me?
If I'm not mistaken,
you mean when I prevented you
from killing Hope.
Yeah, exactly!
If I wasn't there,
are you really saying
that you would've shot
the man right where he stood?
[HOLMES growls]
And why not? At least then
I wouldn't suffer this enigma.
You don't mean that! [grunts]
Hope and I would've
both got what we wanted!
A quick death for him
and for me, the answer
to this damn mystery!
I'm speechless.
You're no sleuth.
All along you were nothing
but a worthless scoundrel.
What?
[WATSON grunts]
If you wish to be a murderer,
then do so on your own.
I refuse to be an accomplice
in your degeneracy.
Good day.
[HOLMES]
How dramatic.
[RAILWAYMAN 10A] The London
train is departing shortly!
Final call for passengers!
[grunts]
[HOLMES]
It's locked?
[HOLMES grumbles]
Fine, then. Food it is.
[WAITER 10A]
Will this table do, sir?
Yeah.
Confound him.
He's like an old maid.
Lecturing me.
[HOLMES]
Hm. Hmm?
I'm switching tables!
[WAITER 10A grunts]
Where to, sir?
Well, now.
Professor.
What are the odds?
Well, now.
Professor.
What are the odds?
[LOUIS]
Sherlock Holmes!
What's he doing here?
I remember.
You and I met while we
were aboard the Noahtic.
The name's Sherlock.
You're quite
famous these days.
I recently read in the
newspapers how you solved
the case of
Lord Drebber's murder.
That is the real mystery.
My intention was for Lestrade
to take all the credit for it.
Either a reporter
sniffed out the truth,
or someone leaked it.
And that's a problem?
As a result, your fame
as a detective has grown.
Isn't that good for business?
[HOLMES]
Hmm. It pays, yes.
But between us, I'm not much
interested in all those dull,
tuppenny-ha'penny cases.
What fascinates me is--
Pardon me, but we were
finishing our meal.
Perhaps sometime later, you--
But you haven't even been served
your dessert or digestif yet.
[LOUIS]
This pest.
[HOLMES] Permit me to bend
your ear for a minute.
By all means, please.
We were just complaining about
how we were growing bored.
[HOLMES] You see, I went to
York to investigate a case
only for it to end up
being a total bust.
Well, that certainly is a pity.
A damn shame. And get this--
I was convinced it was
another in a series of deaths
involving noblemen.
There's a series of them?
Yes. Two so far.
And both have commonalities that
I believe link them together.
The victims, Enders and
Drebber, were aristocrats.
Additionally, their
scandals and misdeeds
were brought to
the public's attention.
And in glorious fashion,
I might add.
But there's one
other trait they share.
In both cases,
a mastermind was operating
behind the scenes.
To the first point,
it doesn't strike me as
being particularly solid.
Two similar events reveal a
coincidence, not a pattern.
Second, the existence
of this mastermind--
isn't it merely
your own presumption?
Well, you'd be
correct, except
my suspicions were
recently confirmed.
This individual
made me a proposal,
extended via Jefferson Hope.
A most interesting one.
If I ended Hope's life,
they would reveal
their identity.
[WILLIAM]
That is quite the odd bargain.
[HOLMES]
Isn't it?
But I didn't accept the terms
and refused to shoot Hope.
[WILLIAM]
A wise decision.
[HOLMES] However, after
he was taken into custody,
I went to visit him,
where he told me a secret.
He felt compelled to reveal
to me who his benefactor was.
The name of the mastermind.
To my shock,
the person he named
is sitting here.
William James Moriarty.
[LOUIS]
Is that the truth or a bluff?
Finding out about
Brother would be simple
if he had sought out
information aboard the Noahtic.
After all,
there aren't many young college
mathematics professors
who are also
sons of aristocrats.
[LOUIS]
Also, after his arrest,
we've been keeping
a close eye on Hope
and would have seen if
he had contact with anyone.
[LOUIS]
Meaning, this must be a ruse.
Brother's name
is still a secret.
Holmes doesn't know.
There's just one problem.
If William calls his bluff,
he'll acknowledge we were
monitoring Hope closely.
Damn it. Holmes, you bastard.
You need to be removed
before it's too late.
I confess...
...that you've made
a most amusing assertion.
However, it is impossible to
prove something I did not do.
And besides,
the burden of proof would
be your responsibility
seeing as you're the detective.
[HOLMES laughing]
A joke! I'm kidding!
There's a case of probatio
diabolica. Too good!
Really! [chuckles]
However, if you were
indeed this mastermind,
just how would you
reply in this instance?
[WILLIAM chuckles]
[HOLMES]
Hm?
"Come and catch me if you can...
...Mister Holmes."
Hmm!
Yes, I suspect you
would derive satisfaction
at hearing those words,
detective.
[laughs]
[HOLMES]
You really are one of a kind.
Judging by your response,
it sounds like my joke
was well received.
Yeah!
You and I are going
to get along famously!
[LESTRADE]
Holmes.
Ah? So there you are.
Well, tell me, who might
these gentlemen be?
This is the Moriarty family's
second son, William,
and his adoptive
younger brother, Louis.
Is that right?
[LOUIS]
Mm.
[LOUIS] Our family...
Just how much does he know?
Please, excuse the interruption.
I am Detective Inspector
Lestrade of Scotland Yard,
at your service.
[WILLIAM] The Lestrade?
It's an honor, sir.
[WOMAN 10A screams]
[GROUP gasps]
[WOMAN 10A gasps]
[LESTRADE]
What's wrong?
Well, I heard a loud
sound in the neighboring
compartment just moments ago.
And when I looked through
the window I saw...
[LESTRADE gasps]
[LESTRADE grunts]
Door's locked!
Holmes, this can't be good.
Yeah. Very dead.
Have a look.
It was quite clearly a murder.
Murder?
So, William,
if you don't have any pressing
matters before we reach London,
how about a friendly competition
to see which of us
finds the culprit first?
[LESTRADE]
Huh? You're not serious!
This is a murder,
not one of your games!
I accept. No doubt
it'll prove entertaining.
However,
this case seems more complicated
than at first glance.
[GROUP]
Huh?
[HOLMES] Next time
on Moriarty the Patriot  .
"The Two Detectives. Act Two."